Lord, I already know y'all gonna come for me on this one.
Juneteenth probably shouldn't be our National Emancipation Day because
it ain't going down like folks be saying it went down.
I mean, yeah, Major General Gordon Granger did sail into Galveston Bay, Texas that day
and formally announced emancipation of the state.
But June 19th was an un-end, nor was it our collective independence.
Let's unpack it.
So the South loses the Civil War and the Confederate government collapses.
Lincoln then issues an executive order, the Emancipation Proclamation,
to take effect January 1, 1863.
What some don't know is that the proclamation only applied to rebel states,
namely Alabama, Arkansas, Florida, Georgia, Mississippi, Northern South Carolina, and Texas.
Specifically, it said all persons held as slaves within the rebellious states,
now and henceforth, shall be free.
The executive order exempted states occupied by the Union and left slavery untouched in
Delaware, Kentucky, Maryland, and Missouri, also called border states.
These were slave-holding states that just didn't secede from the Union.
So on June 19th, 1865, while slavery was federally illegal in Texas,
it was legal and would remain so until the 13th Amendment was ratified by a three-fourths majority
on December 6th, 1865.
Now, the records suggest that New Jersey and Delaware weren't particularly excited
about giving up their human property.
They were the two northern states to initially reject the amendment,
ratifying it sometime later on January 23rd, 1866, and February 12th, 1901, respectively.
So just like the 4th of July, not all of us were free, even on Juneteenth.
We'll see you next week.